Inventory of the Rostislav Evdokimov papers
Hoover Institution Archives
Rostislav Evdokimov papers
1920-2000
99041
Evdokimov, Rostislav, 1950-
9 manuscript boxes (3.6 linear feet)
Hoover Institution Archives Stanford, California 94305-6010
Correspondence, writings, memoranda, newspaper issues, election campaign literature, other printed matter, photographs, and video tapes, relating to activities of the Narodno-Trudovoĭ Soiuz and other anti-communist and labor organizations in the Soviet Union, and to political conditions in the Soviet Union and post-Soviet Russia, and the city of Saint Petersburg
Administrative Information
Access
Collection is open for research.
The Hoover Institution Archives only allows access to copies of audiovisual items. To listen to sound recordings or to view videos or films during your visit, please contact the Archives at least two working days before your arrival. We will then advise you of the accessibility of the material you wish to see or hear. Please note that not all audiovisual material is immediately accessible.
Acquisition Information
Acquired by the Hoover Institution Archives in 1999.
Accruals
Materials may have been added to the collection since this finding aid was prepared. To determine if this has occurred, find the collection in Stanford University's online catalog at http://searchworks.stanford.edu/. Materials have been added to the collection if the number of boxes listed in the online catalog is larger than the number of boxes listed in this finding aid.
Related Materials
SMOT (Svobodnoe mezhprofessional'noe ob'edinenie trudiashchikhsia) records, Hoover Institution Archives
Boris V. Prianishnikov papers, Hoover Institution Archives
Narodno-trudovoĭ soiuz samizdat collection, Hoover Institution Archives
Constantin W. Boldyreff papers, Hoover Institution Archives
Oleg Nikolaevich Moskvin papers, Hoover Institution Archives
Biographical Note
29 November 1950 Born, Leningrad, Soviet Union (Saint Petersburg, Russia)
1968 Admitted to the Leningrad State University, first to the Faculty of Physics, then the Faculty of History
1971 Joined the Narodno-trudovoĭ soiuz (People's Labor Union)
1972 Expelled from the university
1972-1982 Worked on geological and geophysical expeditions in Soviet Union
1979 Joined the SMOT-Svobodnoe mezhprofessional'noe ob'edinenie trudiashchikhsia (Free Inter- professional Trade Union)
1980-1981 Co-editor of the underground newsletter SMOT
1982 Member of the French and Swedish PEN (Poets, Essayists, and Novelists) Club
1982-1983 Arrested for campaigning for free trade unions in the Soviet Union, sentenced to 5 years in Perm labor camp
1986 Author, Stikhi
1987 Granted amnesty, returned to Leningrad
1987 Founder and leader of the Leningrad group of the International Society for Human Rights
1988 Reinstated in the faculty of history at Leningrad State University (graduated in 1992)
1988-1991 Editor in Chief, Petropolis
1991-1994 Council member of the NTS, member of the editorial board of Posev
1994 Member of the Russian PEN Club
1995 Author, Liudskie poteri SSSR v period vtoroi mirovoi voiny
2000 Author, Posle molchaniia
Scope and Content of Collection
The Rostislav Evdokimov papers relate to activities of the Narodno-Trudovoĭ Soiuz (NTS) and other anticommunist and labor organizations in the Soviet Union, as well as political conditions in the Soviet Union, post-Soviet Russia, and the city of Saint Petersburg. The collection consists of correspondence, writings, memoranda, newspaper issues, election campaign literature, printed matter, photographs, and video tapes.
The bulk of the collection dates from 1987 through 2000, after Evdokimov, a writer and social activist, was released from labor camp. He took on leadership roles in the International Society for Human Rights and St. Petersburg branch of the NTS, as well as being an active member of the Editorial board of the NTS publication Posev.
The collection consists of six series, each presenting different aspects of Evdokimov's activities. The Narodno-trudovoĭ Soiuz (NTS) Saint-Petersburg branch materials and the Election campaigns file record Evdokimov's activities as a leader of the Saint-Petersburg political group and his participation in local elections.
While working on his writings, Evdokimov collected material reflecting his interests in the social, politica,l and economic situation in the Soviet Union, post-Soviet Russia, and former Soviet republics. This material in the Subject file, became a foundation for his published political books and articles found in the Writings. The Printed matter and Video recordings series contain additional documents reflecting NTS activities and political events.
Indexing Terms
The following terms have been used to index the description of this collection in the library's online public access catalog.
Narodno-trudovoĭ soiuz.; Anti-communist movements--Soviet Union.; Labor movement--Soviet Union.; Political prisoners--Soviet Union.; Dissenters--Soviet Union.; Soviet Union--Politics and government--1985-1991.; Russia (Federation)--Politics and government--1991-; Videotapes.
Collection Contents
- Narodno-trudovoĭ Soiuz (NTS) Saint Petersburg branch materials, 1987-1997 (Box 1-3)
  Includes correspondence, address books, members list, reports, minutes, statements, proposals and proclamations, speeches and writings, and clippings regarding NTS activities in the city of Saint Petersburg. Arranged in chronological order.
  - 1987 (Folder 1: 1-2)
  - 1989 (Folder 1: 3)
  - 1990 (Folder 1: 4-16)
  - 1991 (Folder 2: 1-7)
  - 1992 (Folder 2: 8-13)
  - 1993 (Folder 2: 14-15, Folder 3: 1-2)
  - 1994 (Folder 3: 3-4)
  - 1995 (Folder 3: 5-6)
  - 1996 (Folder 3: 7-11)
  - 1997 (Folder 3: 12-13)
- Election campaigns file, 1990-1998 (Box 3-4)
  Consists of speeches, writings, notes, proclamations, leaflets, and clippings related to elections at the city and state level. Arranged by public office
  - Leningrad City Soviet of People's Deputies, 1990 (Folder 3: 14)
  - State Duma, 1993, 1995 (Folder 3: 15-16)
  - City Assembly, Saint Petersburg, 1994 (Folder 4: 1-2)
  - Governor of Saint Petersburg, 1996 (Folder 4: 3)
  - Municipal Soviets Deputies, Saint Petersburg, 1997-1998 (Folder 4: 4-7)
  - Legislative Assembly, 1998 (Folder 4: 8-13)
- Subject File, 1920-2000, bulk 1988-2000 (Box 4-7)
  Contains copies of documents, notes, clippings, and printed matter related to Evdokimov's research on a wide varieties of topics, as well as his articles and other writings. Original subject order was maintained, though files with similar titles have been consolidated. Arranged alphabetically.
  - Abkhazia, 1989 (Folder 4: 14)
  - Armenia, 1994 (Folder 4: 15)
  - The Constitution of Russian Federation, 1990-1993 (Folder 5: 1-2)
  - Dagestan, circa 1990 (Folder 5: 3)
  - Ecology, 1990 (Folder 5: 4)
  - Estonia, 1988-1995 (Folder 5: 5-7)
  - Federation of Independent Trade Unions of Russia, 1990 (Folder 5: 8)
  - Informal social organizations documents and press releases, 1988-1989 (Folder 5: 9-10)
  - International child adoption from Russia, 1996-1998 (Folder 5: 11-13)
  - International Society for Human Rights, 1984-1994 (Folder 5: 14-15)
  - Karabakh, 1988-1989 (Folder 6: 1-2)
  - Land ownership in Russia, 1991-1995 (Folder 6: 3)
  - Latvia, 1988-1990 (Folder 6: 4-6)
  - National question, 1989-1991 (Folder 6: 7)
  - National security, 1939 and 1994 (Folder 6: 8)
    Includes O vneshnei politike Sovetskogo Soiuza, report by V. M. Molotov, 1939
  - Natsional'no-Patrioticheskii Front "Pamiat'," periodicals and clippings, 1920, 1986-1990 (Folder 6: 9-10)
    Includes Russian translation The International Jew, by Henry Ford, 1920
  - Political parties and organizations in Russia, 1990-2000 (Folder 6: 11-16, Folder 7: 1)
  - Russian press from remote locations, 1990-1992 (Folder 7: 2-3)
  - Samizdat, 1988-1990 (Folder 7: 4)
  - Social and economic situation in Russia, 1991-1992 (Folder 7: 5)
  - Soviet army, 1989-1995 (Folder 7: 6-8)
  - Soviet "psychiatry,", 1989-1992 (Folder 7: 9)
  - Soviet West, 1989-1993 (Folder 7: 10-11)
  - Ukraine, 1988-1991 (Folder 7: 12)
  - Zemskii soiuz, 1985, 1997
    Includes Samoupravlenie i svoboda v Rossii, by S. Pushkarev, 1985
- Writings, 1990-2000 (Box 8)
  Includes books and articles on political issues. Arranged by the title in chronological order. See also Subject file.
  - Novaia metla v Mariinskom dvortse, 1990 (Folder 8: 1)
  - Vne stroia, 1999 (Folder 8: 2)
  - Zapiski lzhesvidetelia, 1999 (Folder 8: 3)
  - Posle molchaniia, 2000 (Folder 8: 4)
- Printed matter, 1991-2000 (Box 8-9)
  Contains printed material related to Evdokimov's political research. Arranged by title in chronological order
  - Ten' topora, by V. Rybakov, 1991 (Folder 8: 5)
  - Gosudarstvo i ekonomika, by B. Pushkarev, 1993 (Folder 8: 6)
  - Kalendar'-pamiatka NTS, 1995 (Folder 8: 7)
  - Rossiia 1913 god, 1995 (Folder 8: 8)
  - Posev, 1953-1959, 2000 (Folder 8: 9-10)
  - The White Guard, calendar, 2000 (Folder 8: 11)
  - Kak i pochemu ia strelial v glavaria totalitarnogo gosudarstva M. Gorbacheva, by A. A. Shmonov, 2001 (Folder 9: 1)
    Includes handwritten copy
- Video recordings, 1988-1991 (Box 9: 1)
  Consists of professional and home video recordings of political events on VHS tapes. Includes a detailed, handwritten list of contents with comments for each VHS tape
  - List of contents, 1991 (Folder 9: 2)
  - Political life in Leningrad and Georgia, 1988-1989 (Folder 9: Tape 1)
    Includes interview of Zviad Gamsakhurdia, 1988
  - History of the NTS, 1991 (Folder 9: Tape 2)
  - Democratic meetings in Estonia, 1988 (Folder 9: Tape 3)
  - NTS conference in Saint Petersburg, 1990 (Folder 9: Tape 4)
  - Interview of Evgenii Romanovich Ostrovskii (Romanov), President of the NTS, Frankfurt, 1990 (Folder 9: Tape 5)